<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phones on Knurdtech</title>
    <link>http://knurdtech.com/categories/phones/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Phones on Knurdtech</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://knurdtech.com/categories/phones/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Nokia Lumia Comparison - Lumia 710, 800, and 900</title>
      <link>http://knurdtech.com/nokia-lumia-comparison-lumia-710-800-and-900/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://knurdtech.com/nokia-lumia-comparison-lumia-710-800-and-900/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;features-they-have-in-common:16be26762203e3ee2f88d30baf8e45f5&#34;&gt;Features they have in common:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nokia is making a new run at the US market with the Windows Phone 7 &amp;ldquo;Mango&amp;rdquo; OS. While Nokia is very well known in other countries for building quality phones, it has been awhile since they have had an impact in the states. We are analyzing the differences between the Lumia 710, Lumia 800, and soon to be released Lumia 900. First up, what they all have in common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processor: 1.4 GHz Snapdragon S2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graphics: Qualcomm Adreno 205&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memory: 512 MB SDRAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screen: Capacitive touch with ClearBlack technology and Gorilla glass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolution: 480 x 800 WVGA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera: All include a rear facing camera with autofocus though the specs vary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nokia-lumia-710:16be26762203e3ee2f88d30baf8e45f5&#34;&gt;Nokia Lumia 710&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display: 3.7 inch TFT LCD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera: 5 MP with f/2.4 aperture and single LED flash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Battery: 1300 mAh capable of 7 hours talk, 400 h standby, 38 h music playback, or 5.5 h video playback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mass memory (storage): 8 GB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nokia-lumia-800:16be26762203e3ee2f88d30baf8e45f5&#34;&gt;Nokia Lumia 800&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display: 3.7 inch AMOLED PenTile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera: 8 MP Carl Zeiss optics with f/2.2 aperture and dual LED flash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Battery: 1450 mAh capable of 9.5 hours talk, 335 h standby, 55 h music playback, or 6.5 h video playback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mass memory (storage): 16 GB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nokia-lumia-900:16be26762203e3ee2f88d30baf8e45f5&#34;&gt;Nokia Lumia 900&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display: 4.3 inch AMOLED RGB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data: 4G LTE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera (rear): 8 MP same specs as Lumia 800&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera (front): 1 MP for video calling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Battery: 1830 mAh capable of 7 hours talk, 300 h standby, 60 h music playback, or 6.5 h video playback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mass memory (storage): 16 GB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-and-conclusions:16be26762203e3ee2f88d30baf8e45f5&#34;&gt;Summary and Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lumia 710 has a different body style than the &lt;sup&gt;800&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;900&lt;/sub&gt;. The Lumia 800 copies the Nokia N9 while the Lumia 900 looks similar but grows for the bigger screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going from the Lumia 710 to Lumia 800 gains better looks (opinion), slightly better camera, a little bigger battery, and 8 GB additional storage. The extra storage may be important since none of these phones have an SD slot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving from the Lumia 800 to the Lumia 900 you basically gain screen size, a front facing camera, and 4G LTE support. The larger battery benefit is mostly negated by the increased battery usage of the larger screen and possibly LTE. Although the screen resolution remains the same, the lack of PenTile subpixels makes it more clear on the larger display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately it comes down to: Does a Windows Phone work for you?  Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symbian Belle experience on Nokia 701</title>
      <link>http://knurdtech.com/symbian-belle-experience-nokia-701/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://knurdtech.com/symbian-belle-experience-nokia-701/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;importing-contacts-from-android:d6754a4efc00ca2ed2a11e2a0ff8c621&#34;&gt;Importing Contacts from Android:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nokia only provides directions to copy contacts over from another Nokia phone. However, importing contacts by other methods is quite easy. Here we are using a generic .vcf import that works well coming from an Android device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;liberating-your-contacts-from-google:d6754a4efc00ca2ed2a11e2a0ff8c621&#34;&gt;Liberating your contacts from Google&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, make sure your Android contacts are synced with your phone&amp;rsquo;s Google account. Most people leave sync enabled but you may check by going to&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then sign into your Google account from a computer (signing into Gmail will accomplish this). Now paste the following in your address bar: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/takeout/#custom:contacts&#34;&gt;https://www.google.com/takeout/#custom:contacts&lt;/a&gt;. (If you want to find it the long way, drop down from your email and select account settings. In account settings, select &amp;ldquo;data liberation&amp;rdquo;, then &amp;ldquo;download your data&amp;rdquo;, followed by &amp;ldquo;choose services.&amp;rdquo; For our purposes, all we need are contacts.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The file downloads as a compressed .zip file. Use your preferred extraction tool (download 7-zip if you need one) to extract all .vcf files with contact data. In my case this was only one file &amp;ldquo;My Contacts.vcf&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;importing-contacts-to-nokia-belle:d6754a4efc00ca2ed2a11e2a0ff8c621&#34;&gt;Importing contacts to Nokia Belle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now mount your Symbian phone to the computer in &amp;ldquo;Mass storage&amp;rdquo; mode and copy your .vcf contact file(s) to E: Mass memory -&amp;gt; Other -&amp;gt; Contacts. Note: I did try putting this file in other places and it was not recognized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost done. Simply open Contacts, tap the options menu in lower right -&amp;gt; Copy contact card -&amp;gt; From other memory. That&amp;rsquo;s it! Your Nokia phone should have all your contacts now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nokia-message-indicator-won-t-stop-blinking:d6754a4efc00ca2ed2a11e2a0ff8c621&#34;&gt;Nokia message indicator won&amp;rsquo;t stop blinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manual is pretty worthless here as it only states &amp;ldquo;if the message indicator is blinking, your Inbox folder may be full.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick search reveals the cause to lie in messages stored on your SIM card (left over from your old phone). A relatively simple fix although a little hidden in the menus. Open messaging -&amp;gt; options -&amp;gt; View folders -&amp;gt; options -&amp;gt; SIM messages. Now delete all those messages and your indicator should stop flashing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-contacts-on-belle:d6754a4efc00ca2ed2a11e2a0ff8c621&#34;&gt;Using contacts on Belle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So refreshing. Select a contact and Belle presents all contact methods for that person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use certain contacts frequently? Assign those people as favorites and they always appear at the top of the contact list. You can also assign contacts as shortcuts or to a contact widget on one of your home screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a follow up post, I will add social network integration and evaluate configuration options. Of course I will test out the VOIP / SIP integration as well. Nokia usually shines in that area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UPDATE 7/20/12: After using Nokia Belle for a few months, I can no longer recommend it. When it works it is fine but all too often it either freezes or behaves incorrectly. Unfortunately this leaves me with no favorite mobile OS. I&amp;rsquo;m also not a fan of Android, iOS, or Windows Phone 7 in their current states (although I can at least live with Android).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that Blackberry 10, currently slated for a 2013 release, or Windows Phone 8 will make major strides &lt;strong&gt;OR&lt;/strong&gt; that Jolla (a company consisting of former Nokia employees) beats the odds and does something amazing with the MeeGo platform.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samsung Captivate first impressions</title>
      <link>http://knurdtech.com/samsung-captivate-first-impressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://knurdtech.com/samsung-captivate-first-impressions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally broke down and purchased one&amp;hellip;been playing with it about a week.  So now it is time for first thoughts about the phone, Android 2.1, and the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the Samsung Captivate is nothing short of amazing.  The size is perfect: a brilliant 4&amp;rdquo; Super AMOLED screen that easily fits in my pocket.  Any smaller or larger would be a sacrifice now.  The CPU/GPU (processor and mobile graphics) combo is the best currently available.  As with any technology&amp;hellip;that won&amp;rsquo;t be for long.  I have already mentioned some upcoming dual-core mobile CPUs in other posts.  But the Samsung Hummingbird 1 GHz plays great with Android 2.1 and will absolutely smoke with 2.2.  The only current problems with the phone are GPS issues.  Fixes have been posted on the internet but Samsung is also releasing an official update next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first experience with Android.  Unfortunately it&amp;rsquo;s a customized UI with added AT&amp;amp;T apps.  I haven&amp;rsquo;t rooted or otherwise hacked anything yet.  That said&amp;hellip;it&amp;rsquo;s still a great mobile operating system so far.  I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to Android 2.2 and tinkering with more things.  Integration with Google apps are great but how far are you willing to give up privacy?  I&amp;rsquo;m currently using gmail, google calendar, and contact sync.  Also absolutely love typing with Swype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which only leaves the network.  They &amp;ldquo;caught&amp;rdquo; me and upgraded the data plan to one that is smartphone appropriate.  You know&amp;hellip;data use on one particular phone should cost more than the same amount of data from another phone.  And an appropriate 3G data on some phones is a requirement even if you plan to live on WiFi&amp;hellip;and even if you did not purchase on subsidized contract.  I could dedicate a whole post (rant) based on all this but I digress.  The sum of the equation is that while they are going to lose me as a customer&amp;hellip;it has absolutely nothing to do with this sexy piece of hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motorola Droid X / Droid 2 and Samsung Galaxy S</title>
      <link>http://knurdtech.com/motorola-droid-x-droid-2-and-samsung-galaxy-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://knurdtech.com/motorola-droid-x-droid-2-and-samsung-galaxy-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Still holding on to a Nokia e71 waiting for something that really stands out.  These phones almost fit the bill but the Droid X ends up being a smaller upgrade than initially thought.  Verizon fans considering a Droid X or Droid 2?  Hold out a month or so longer to give the Samsung Fascinate a fair shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First a look at the details of the new Droids.  Droid 2 takes the more evolutionary upgrade route which still houses a physical keypad and a 3.7&amp;rdquo; LCD display.  Droid X attempts to please multimedia enthusiasts with a 4.3&amp;rdquo; LCD display, HDMI out, and 720p HD video capture.  Both Droids receive a processor bump with the TI OMAP3640 and also 512 MB RAM (up from 256).  Compared to the original Droid (TI OMAP3430) it&amp;rsquo;s a smaller die size which allows an increase from 550 MHz to 1 GHz.  Unfortunately, the upgraded processors still use the same integrated GPU (PowerVR SGX530).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In swoops the Samsung Galaxy S line that will wind up on all four major US carriers (each slightly different and with custom names).  Main attractions to this phone include an upgraded GPU (SGX540) to go along with the 1 GHz Cortex-A8 processor and a stunning 4&amp;rdquo; Super AMOLED display.  The Samsung Vibrant (T-Mobile&amp;rsquo;s version) is already confirmed for July 21st release.  Captivate (AT&amp;T;), Epic 4G (Sprint), and Fascinate (Verizon) should follow shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Samsung display and better graphics processor definitely makes it a contender.  Early versions of the Droid Incredible used the same Super AMOLED.  However, Samsung manufactures them and appear to be keeping the majority for themselves.  Motorola had to switch to Sony Super TFT LCD in an attempt to catch up with demand.  They have not even advertised the change in hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these phones will be out over the next couple of months so it will be interesting to see hands-on reviews.  However, I still find myself holding back for the dual-core processors coming out late this year and early next year.  Those include the OMAP 4400&amp;rsquo;s by TI, Tegra 2 by NVIDIA, U8500 by Sony Ericsson, and dual-core Snapdragon by Qualcomm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>